[SPEAKER_01]: What's the question?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at the point of view...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anicca applies to the point of view, which you said, rather than to things like your book, or your lamp, or your... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a leaf.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to apply that...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to apply, or rather you can say anicca can apply to both, through the point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to apply anicca to the things, as it sometimes might have been done, you need to... you have to apply it only to those things upon which your view depends, upon which your sense of self depends, upon the which of your center of... upon the which the center of your experience depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, upon things that you took as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not... Anicca will never be understood in its... in its... in its... in its nature, if you try to approach it, think about it, as a... as a some sort of law of physics or whatever, whereby everything is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, everything will come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might be true in theoretical sense, but in terms of freeing you from suffering, that understanding simply won't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because anicca results in freedom from suffering when you see your own sense of self, your own center of experience undermined by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at the random things that you don't care, you have absolutely no emotional connection to whatsoever, like, you simply... they're simply irrelevant to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can... you can... like, you can see them as impermanent as much as you like.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't make a big difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said before, people associate impermanence with witnessing of the destruction of a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Witnessing its ending means, ah, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that can never be applied to your own point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that would require you to see your own seeing as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, in order to see that, you have to see your own seeing ending.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see the end of your own seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't make... well, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that would require you to step outside of the experience as a whole, the five aggregates, and then see them disappear, and then say, okay, they are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's that's simply inconceivable, because you can't step outside of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there is no outside of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when you think about outside of the five aggregates, that experience as a whole is within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then it becomes clear that the impermanence that the Buddha was teaching about, that does pertain to the five aggregates and the freedom from the whole thing, cannot possibly be the impermanence of, of, oh, I just looked, I just seen a thing being destroyed, thus it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a worldly impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, as I think we discussed before, anicca,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more than just what's thought as impermanence, which means you should probably find a better translation for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, whatever translation is found, they probably need to be explained heavily, because people already have deeply rooted notions of impermanence, permanence, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, everything is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't really free you from suffering, that kind of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, if it's not free from suffering, it means it's not the impermanence that the Buddha was teaching about, that directly results in the recognition of not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, anicca is closer related to the lack of control over things, lack of mastery, than it's related to the common notion of impermanence, of witnessing a thing's ending.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, by saying, by experiencing that point of view, by seeing it phenomenologically, you can't say that it is permanent or impermanent, in the sense of, no, because
[SPEAKER_00]: There would just be an assumption, because you would have to step out of that point of view to be able to see the flow.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would have to fall away from the phenomenology, from the mindfulness of that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you call it permanent, even if you call it eternal, you will have to fall away from that experience, because exactly, yeah, permanent or impermanent, it's applied to it secondarily, as an assumption on top of it, while in reality, what your experience shows you, it's basically
[SPEAKER_01]: There is that center of that experience, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a sense of infinite, always being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Infinite, kind of, infinite, sort of, appearance, in the terms of the infinite possibilities, which means infinite possibilities of being there, which means being there infinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is then confused as lasting forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no matter how far the thing reaches, like, there is no end in sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that whole structure is swept away,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means none of it can remain standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you don't apply the idea of anicca to things individually, or things that you can gather through your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You apply it to the structure of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point of view and...
[SPEAKER_01]: The very root of it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's abandoned on that level, through seeing that you have no control, no mastery over it, you have certainly nothing to do with its arising, you realize, for that reason,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't even say, for that reason, it will come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, it will induce people to think, oh, so I will witness the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, better to say, for that reason, it will never be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you see it as truly impermanent, as truly arisen on its own, independent of you, you're absolutely... it's inconceivable for you to have any say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that reason, it will never ever be yours, even in a remote, the wireless or the fantasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even access it, even in that theoretical, like, idea of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that realization pervades your mind, through and through and through and through and through, you will simply stop appropriating anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what arises, on what level, in what sense, how, what experience, it's just... the idea of taking it up is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the point of view is basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when nothing can be taken as mine, no sense of self, in that long, infinitely everlasting thing, can ever be maintained anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you're seeing, as in common to every experience on the more particular level, what you're seeing on the more general level, is the five aggregates, or one among them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just different aspects of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, as a structure, they always have to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, as a structure, they will not be discerned, even as a structure, if those particular things are not arisen beforehand, not given.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it feeds itself, mutually determined, depending on where you look at.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that that center, sense of self, that it's kind of in the center, it sort of feels like
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always seeing these things, witnessing these things, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to deny that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to try to remove that, in a sense of this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's there, as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have to do is see that, also, as something that has arisen on its own, in result to other things that have already arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, even that sense of self, you can't own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly... Because if you would
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, in theory, if you were to truly be the master of that sense of self, if you tell it to stop arising, it should stop arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you tell it to rise like this, it should rise like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, impermanence is found right in, like, in the heart of non-mastery things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're arising, you're not controlling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can be in control of, like, I think we spoke about a few days ago, to various different options that presents to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, when it comes down to choosing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you can choose this or this or that or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you cannot choose or not choose is the whole structure of choice that you are basically, well, imprisoned by.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're within it, you have no choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, I'm not going to choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just chose.
[SPEAKER_01]: I refrain from any form of
[SPEAKER_01]: Choice or action?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a form of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will keep revolving around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't step outside of it through that choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way you can step outside, through that kind of fully enclosed picture, is if you start discerning it from inside as something that actually, well, cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, no matter what choices you make within that, can't pertain to you either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor the result of those can eventually pertain to you either, because you abandon the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is only possible once the moral behavior, the restraint and sīla have been developed and purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, if you just take it abstractly, you can say, okay, so it doesn't matter what I do doesn't apply to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it does.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you're bound by it, it applies to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there is no the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no discernible beginning of when these things started applying to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it is gratuitous setup.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Abhijā is a gratuitous parasite, as Dīnabhira called it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it shouldn't be there, but the fact that it's there, means it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you undo it, the only reason you're able to undo it, is because it was never meant to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that it was never meant to be there, you placed it there, and you maintain it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you discern that actually it cannot be there, it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through purification of the behavior of the body, the speech and the mind, then, eventually, you recognize that no matter what options of your choice are given to you, the nature of the choice, it's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can only choose is good, bad or neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you focus on choosing good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or wholesome, rather.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily, like, good, good, what's accepted, commonly cited as good.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are three choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Three choices for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, yeah, there are only three directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, within those directions, there are more directions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what confuses people in thinking they own things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is, that you were thrown within that center, within that inevitability of choice, means you don't really own that either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what particular choice you make on the result of that inevitability of that choice, it doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It matters practically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It matters on a particular level, whether it's wholesome or unwholesome, whether it's going to contribute to the maintenance of that, like, delusional view.
[SPEAKER_01]: or undermining of the delusional view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it matters in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fundamentally, from the point of view of the five aggregates, it doesn't really matter, because the nature of the choice is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why somebody who does understand that nature of choice and abandonment, he goes beyond good and bad, beyond wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't have to go, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not hard to look for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just take up any experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take the experience right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sense of... call it self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sense of the... that which is in common... that... that which is in common to all the different experiences you can get through... through... through different senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: The... the center of the experience, the... the... the knee or the point of view,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you're more spiritually inclined, you can call it the observer, as I said before, the pure awareness, the knower, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Call it whatever you like.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you take it to be yours, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't take it to be yours, that's a solution.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that thing can still remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... because... because it's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when there are things, the five aggregates, and when there is a point of view, they will have... it has to be centered somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you end up assuming the nature of that center as permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you take it out to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no center if there are no other things defining the center.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive, oh, this is in the center of what?
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is nothing defining it, center will not be discerned at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just will not emerge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how... and that center can always look the same, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the center of different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the fact that there are different things, that's what defines the center.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even your sense of self, then, is defined by all the other particular things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And certainly, if that sense of self is taken to be mine, to be my own self, that's defined by all other particular things that you own, that you took to be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Implicitly, a little bit, a little bit here, a little bit there, they all contribute to them, this center of self, that's in common to all of them, feels as like really mine, really personal, really dear to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what needs to be removed out of it, not the actual sense of the center of the experience, the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the problem there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove that ownership and then it's what you have left, it's what you would have called individuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the center of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The center of that, those five aggregates, the most common center, the most the most prevailing characteristic of a center of those five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's different to different people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, different individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's the same, let's say, if it's two individuals the same, the fact is, there are two, thus they're different.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's one, there's two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they're completely mirrored, it's still two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's two different things, two different individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that sense, you can't have, like, two five aggregates to be identical, because if they would be identical, they would be indistinguishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, a place whereby things are experienced.
[SPEAKER_00]: A place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, no, not quite.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not experiencing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this experience of things generates the sense of the center.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it depends how you define here.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you define here as opposite of yonder, then it's not here, because you won't find it here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's including... it has to include both, so it would be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that center, it's in regard to particular experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not in the center, nor is the center in the
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just when there are senses, there is a center, there's a sense of a center in regards to senses, which is exactly how the mind and the senses are kind of arranged, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: They meet in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: They all center in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They all gather there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see that even the arrangement of the six senses, the five senses and the mind is the sixth,
[SPEAKER_01]: All it implies, already, already reflects that structure of, like, these particular things generating meeting up in this center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the mind will simply not be discerned if there are no five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be nothing defining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if there is, if there is no... Well, it's not, it's not a perfect analogy, but it can give you the idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there are no bricks,
[SPEAKER_01]: Consisting, making this little house, you will have a house.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly will not have a center in that house.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is the center of the house.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you remove all the definition of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, the mind is defined through these five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time, these five senses, well, they will simply not be operable in any way, if there is no mind, if there is no... their recognition in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even that structure already kind of implies the idea of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see how it's not hard to end up assuming the sense of self, the owner, the soul, the me, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because things are arranged in that way and then you just have to kind of put that last little touch to it and make it mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you have to go against that grain, against that seeming kind of arrangement of the self in the center, which is basically a deception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you go against it, not by denying this center of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can take I am...
[SPEAKER_01]: I am me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take that as a valid phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, don't take that to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That whole experience of me, I am, you disown that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you disown that personal center, the personality aspects, because there's no ownership in regard to it, and you just have the individual left, left behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience of these very five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience of this point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience of these preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why ārahants are indistinguishable.
[SPEAKER_01]: External practitioners can't tell them apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why wouldn't they?
[SPEAKER_01]: Individual... You can be individual without being a person.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't be a person without already including the individuality in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm doing the personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, if you appropriate your individuality, you become a person.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fact that you are already a person means that appropriation is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as you can see, it is gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, remove the ownership of your person, of your sense of personality.
[SPEAKER_01]: However vague or general it might be, you remove the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you have left is the individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you remove the ownership of it by seeing that you can't really control it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it could cease at any given moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enough to make you let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not only do it and deny its existence, but certainly stop holding it as yours, as something you are in charge of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, impermanence is... if you want to translate it as impermanence, it's basically more closely related to the things might cease, than actually seeing them cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact that you, your own sense of self, might cease, that's enough to discern the nature of impermanence pertaining to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can't see that might.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, you need thing to be present in order to see that it's possible for it to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you recognize the possibility, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize the nature of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it was permanent, you can't imagine how that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't imagine a thing with... to be... to exist without a possibility to not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, basically, being becomes the reason for its impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because it has a reason, that's why the possibility of its cessation is inherently there, in that nature of that arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to see them cease at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to recognize them arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you discern that nature, you will see that there's the inherent, implicit,
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibility of them to not be, simply because they are right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that possibility, that's enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense of possibility to suffer in the future, it's suffering in itself right now, that possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you might feel great today, tomorrow, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might feel great right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think that next week there might be something that will cause you to suffer some, that's already a form of worry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And worry is unpleasant right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it pertains to the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I am here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm alive, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the next week, I might not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a whole... Where... How long has this been going on for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, how long will it go on for?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly... Yeah, that doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's that little doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that little doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you look at it...
[SPEAKER_01]: It should show.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if you look at it even closer, you can see, oh, how long has this been...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as it has been going on for, there was always possibility for it to not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that reason, for as long as it was going on for, it was impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because it was impermanent in that sense, you have no control over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it was suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, as if you have no control over possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can control this or that, but I can't control all possible possibilities that might befall this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just inconceivable, because control is secondary to those possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's defined by the possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your choice, which is a synonym for people, for putrugenas, a synonym with control.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's defined by things that are possible or not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't choose that which is not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, those possibilities are very uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they undermine not just your present experience, but even your possible choice in regard to those possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's determined by the possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, usually, people could discern possibilities based on the present experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the way it has to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you discern, it becomes apparent that, structurally, possibilities precede the experience as it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're more primordial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, they're simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean the possibilities come first and then these things follow later.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they simultaneously arise, but possibilities are more general in their nature, which means they're, well, deeper, so to speak, in terms of the structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're more fundamental to the nature of a possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what nature of suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's seen as such, means right here, right now, this center, this me, this self, will not be mine, will not feel mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is it possible for you, sitting right here, right now, is it possible for you to die in the next two minutes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in the next in-breath?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, you do know if it's possible or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you don't know... That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there's not even a doubt out.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's just being being kind of obstinately blind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you look at it closely, you don't know that you might die.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, the fact is that you don't know that you might die means you might die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fact that you might die...
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it is 50-50, say, or the fact that it's like one percentage you might die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, there is one chance in a hundred that you might be dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's enough to see this very center of yourself right here, right now, as you speak, as you doubt, as you think about death, as not being yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being able to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were truly yours, there would be simply no possibility of death pertaining to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to doubt whether you can die next moment or not, it's better to turn around, turn... sorry, turn it, turn it differently, and then doubt whether you're going to be alive the next moment or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is obviously, you can see, by doubting whether I'm mortal or not, you give priority to a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you doubt whether I'm mortal or not, you give priority to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: You give priority to a non-sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I said it in the same way for that reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, you can doubt whether you're going to die or you can doubt if you're going to be alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is it possible for you to be alive next moment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I might not be alive, rather than I might die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you have knowledge to it properly, then you can ask either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason why I ask it differently is because, yeah, you said like many people would say, well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, maybe that experience of death, I'll still be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it's maybe for you right here, right now, means maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it means maybe not, it means you're not in control of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're not in control of it, it can't be yours in the future, as a possibility, and certainly not yours right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can look, well, it was certainly not mine even in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the Arhat's knowledge attends to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the present knowledge pertains and pervades his past and the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't even think, even before he was an arahant, when he remembers his patujana time, he doesn't think, I was back then either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that sense of abandoning ownership of your sense of self, it just pervades the whole structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present, past is present, and future is present, and present is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say this center-self, this center of my experience, just feels so real, so permanent, it's just eternal, been around all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that all might be valid, in terms of how it feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not up for debate.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what it is, what is up for debate, is if it's going to stay like that or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you assume,
[SPEAKER_01]: Since all I can remember, it was this sense of self, thus this sense of self will continue.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will be an assumption, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, well, maybe it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that maybe is enough for you to discern, if you look at it closely enough, the impermanence of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because there is that the tiny little thread of maybe in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you start looking at it closer, well, longer and longer, it... it... well, it would be less and less of a thread.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will become more and more like a proper foundation of the experience, the full-on structure of that maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if everything sits upon maybe, I can't own it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can own only that which was given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, I can entertain the idea of ownership in regard to that which was given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means even that entertained idea of ownership is the result of that which was given beforehand, which was already affected by that maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, my whole ownership is not really mine, because it could have been otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not mine right here, right now, because it was affected by that maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever it's in the future, it will certainly not be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's mine, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it has a reason for me, given... and I put everything as my choice, it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was affected by that inherent possibility of maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything that arises is maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe for you, maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means that which has arisen as for you, it's not for you either, because it could have been not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's a similar one when the Buddha asked the man, are there more things that you haven't seen or the things that you've seen?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, of course, well, there are more things that I haven't seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are there more things that you haven't heard than ones that you heard?
[SPEAKER_01]: More things that you haven't tasted than ones that you've tasted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, there are more things that haven't arisen
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for that very reason, you abandon everything that has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that, like, has a reason in the past, everything that arises now, and everything that will arise in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those things that haven't a reason will always remain more numerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if you go back to what I spoke before, what I just said about this possibility of maybe not, maybe yes, maybe it will persist, maybe it will arise in the same way, maybe it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, whatever does arise, there will always be a possibility of it not being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those possibilities will be always more numerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the possibility of maybe not is actually much vaster than everything that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you start looking at your whole experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, you... not just this life, but you can... all of the lives you've been around, you can... you can... you can look at the whole thing as completely circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arisen, but it could have not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that could have not was much vast, much greater.
[SPEAKER_01]: than that which did manifest at some point in time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can think about the future as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever does arise, if you do continue living for a while, whatever does arise, it will arise on the ground of that much vaster non-arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, whatever is given, no matter how great, how how lonely, or how painful, how frightening,
[SPEAKER_01]: It could have not been, and that could have not been, and it wouldn't have been for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much greater.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it could have not been, and that which did come to be, it's certainly not for me, because it came on the basis of all the things that haven't even manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, that which manifests, it's completely circumstantial, determined by all of it that didn't manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, it certainly cannot be mine, or for me, or special, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because every sense of ownership is special.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even if you take a sense of self, it means, yeah, that's why the conceit and ego revolve around that appropriation of your own sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel special.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at the whole thing, including your sense of self, completely circumstantial, random.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncertainism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unsure, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure Ajahn Chah... well, I'm not sure, because I've never met him, but based on other things that I did read of his transcribed talks, I'm pretty positive that he meant it in the right way, when he said everything unsure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, people now just say that as a sort of mantra, but as you can see, you need to do a bit of drilling and digging in order for this maybe or unsure
[SPEAKER_01]: Or uncertain to start to apply correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you'd just be denying everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: What time are you coming?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm sure, I'm sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you like something to eat today?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncertain about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm uncertain about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, are you uncertain about your uncertainty?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because obviously... Yeah, because you can be taking your sense of uncertainty as me, as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: See?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not attached to anything and you're attached to the view if I'm not attached to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it takes a bit more than that, but yeah, yeah, it comes down to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it's... it was always affected by maybe means whatever has arisen, it was more likely to not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because there's always a greater likelihood of things not being, you can... you can... you can then realize, well, there's nothing I can own.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing that will entertain, nothing that will escape this uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's with me for hundreds of years, well, like devas, like they're asked for eons and eons, and yeah, sure, they forget that they were born, because they've been around for so long, their memory lapses, and they do think they're eternal for that reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not accidental that people then entertain the kind of notions of eternity when it comes to the sense of self and the soul.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, it always seems today, it's always like all these particular things might be arising or whatever, and I can see them being destroyed, but this sense of self remains there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's always possibility for you to not remain there, and you don't look at that possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if people start looking at possibility they might die, they start freaking out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, going back to what I was saying, the possibility that I might die or death might happen to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then again, it might be it might be best to ask, am I still going to be alive?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I say death, what happens?
[SPEAKER_01]: It moves the center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, shifts the center of the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will happen to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it becomes... death becomes another external experience that you witness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you remain permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you remain unaffected by that death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is exactly what people think.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say, everybody dies.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I'll experience something, and then it's kind of weird.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even death will be an experience of me with... experience that I'm witnessing, that my sense of self is witnessing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, my sense of self will remain eternal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at, well, will my sense of self remain eternal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fact that it's maybe, the fact that you can't give a hundred percent certain answer
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will never be able to give a hundred percent certain answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can doubt it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can place it in a question by asking, am I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you are a hundred percent certain, if you were truly the owner, even the question of questioning that ownership would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would own the future in the same sense you're owning right here, right now, through the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you come to the answer, yes, I will live forever, the fact that you have asked that question beforehand, means that question of, or rather that possibility of maybe, precedes it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can... whatever you come up with as an answer, it's going to be an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you... it was accessible to doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by doubting it, means you can't really own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no certainty in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by doubting whether you're going to be alive, you recognize that, okay, I'm not in charge of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you... if you convince yourself that you will always be... that your sense of self is eternal, you realize that can always be placed in question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you refrain from doing it, the fact that there is a possibility of it being questioned, means it's subject to that maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's subject to that maybe, then it's not certain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what nitya is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And any, anything, take any, any non-certainty, any uncertainty, sorry, take any uncertainty, take any uncertainty in regard to anything of that nature, it will always be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha, or rather, let's not call it suffering, because suffering would be an over-translation, in the same sense as impermanence would be an over-translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's call it unease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any uncertainty is also uneasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if something is uncertain and uneasy, calling it like a form of concern, that cannot possibly be something you are in control of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because control is completely the opposite of... control is ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Control is ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Control is mastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Control is control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncertainty, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if I'm in control, this is certain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say you're driving a car, and it's like, well, it's uncertain that this car will always go where you sort of steer the wheel, means, oh, so I'm not really in control of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if 99% of the time you are controlling the car, that 1% of it not listening to you means your control was undermined by that relativity.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the time, at any given time of your control, it was always undermined by the possibility of not being your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it was never your control in that personal, eternal sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there it is, the formula.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not be, and it might not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be, and it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, it might not be, and there will not be for me, means a thing is affected by that uncertainty, by that maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever has arisen right here, right now, it could have not arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: means it was uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, it's manifested in a certain way, and that's certain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that whole certainty is undermined by this more general uncertainty that it could have... like, it could have easily not been.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can look at your experiences, like, whatever, your past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever happened to you, it could have not happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, the bad things, everybody wishes that they wouldn't have not... they wouldn't have happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the good things, obviously, you never question.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at the whole thing,
[SPEAKER_01]: Impersonally, so to speak, you will recognize that, yeah, it, these things that have arisen, they could have equally not manifested itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you had no say in their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, so the formula that carries on, thus, it will not be and it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you recognize that then in the future, whatever arises, it will be on a basis of it could have not arisen,
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if it arises in the future, it might arise, sure, but one thing for sure, it will never arise for you, as yours, as mine, because it was always affected by that uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things right here, right now, are affected by that uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, things in the future that arise, if I live that long, let's say, they might arise, but one thing for sure is they will not arise as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if they were mine to begin with, they would never be uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that you find uncertainty first, means whatever arises in the future, whatever experience you go through, it's circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, it can never be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can go through all sorts of experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can live for 200 years,
[SPEAKER_01]: But one thing you will be certain of is that none of it will be arising for you, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: for your sense of self, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: for your independent sense of self that exists completely in charge of all these things that are manifesting for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: they will not be arising for this center, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: this center will not be independent of those things that arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the party formula?
[SPEAKER_01]: The party formula is...
[SPEAKER_01]: No cāsa, no cāme sīla, nā bhavisati, nā me bhavisati.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the literal translation, it might not be, and there might not be for me, which is kind of debatable, they can't agree how to translate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it might not be, it might not be for me, it will not be, and it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's an uncertainty there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the things that are uncertain, right here, right now, even things you're certain of, you can doubt that certainty persists, which means it's uncertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can be certain about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can be certain that it will always remain uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you can be certain about the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you can be certain about suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you can be certain about not taking anything to be in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, nibbāna is... What's that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh... sureity.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's that translation one should sing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a shirt.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're a shirt-off.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I've seen that shirt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Surety.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, maybe I'm pronouncing it wrongly, but surety or sureity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of, of, of confidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you are certain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's a liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unshakable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That form of certainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainty that makes you take everything as uncertain, as a result of that, makes you not take anything as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing is that whatever has arisen, it could have not arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, whatever does arise in the future, it will be equally affected by that circumstantial nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, whatever arises in the future, yeah, that might happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing for sure, it cannot be learnt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can doubt it right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much exactly what I said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said, for one with such view, with this view, that it might not be... Another thing is that you can see that this entire formula pertains to the nature of possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: It refers to it might not be, it might not be for me, or rather it might not be and they might not be for me, it will not be and they will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it attends to the possibility of the right here, right now, and then the future possibility of possibilities are even more sort of removed from that sense of ownership, the fact that they are under the big question mark, might, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever is present right here, right now, you can look at it as like, well, yeah, it is present, it is defined, it is arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it was all on the ground of that maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize, well, it could have... it could have not been easily, equally, in anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, no matter what it is, you can... because why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not in control of your... of your own sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter what... what you've seen, heard, tasted, touched, smelled, thought of, you realize it could have not been.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of things that... that taste, that see, like your eye, eh... things that smell, your nose, things that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind will always be uncertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense, they will not necessarily persist.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they don't persist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that you access through them is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, you can't, as you can see, you can't be destroying your own eye to see the nature of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you won't be able to see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you see that there is a
[SPEAKER_01]: In the heart of it, there is a possibility that it might not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you realize, oh, yeah, that's why I can't own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it might not be automatically means, if it is, it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said, for one with such view, it is to be expected that there will be no attraction towards being for him and there will be no repulsion towards cessation of being in him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Poorly putting his heart into this, his mind into this, into this understanding, a monk could easily cut the lower fetters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you ponder on this long enough, and drill the understanding of it on and on and on, the Buddha said that he wouldn't be, before long,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you, if you not just disown everything right here, right now, through the discernment of being it uncertain, being it permanent, you also, anything future, no matter how remote, how unmindful of it you might be, you, you disown it as well, through recognizing
[SPEAKER_01]: Through simple recognition that you can't own it, because it's always coming on the background of, well, maybe not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it cools you down, doesn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said, actually, I said that, I didn't think of this, but it's pretty much the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I said that people to really
[SPEAKER_01]: doubt their own life.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense, if they were really put in question, whether they're going to exist the next moment or not, the concern and worry, like a caterer for an untrained mind, would arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can be applying it in that external manner of saying, oh, well, everybody dies, I'll die, but you don't really question their point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you look at the point of view, your sense of self, your center of experience, this soul, whatever you want to call it,
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how permanent, how there, how stable it feels, if you just look at it honestly and say, will it, will this thing be there next moment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you know that if it is there, it will not be for you, because you doubted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if somebody, if an untrained mind, can also look in the direction of death, with death, that's what death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will this center of experience be there next moment?
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, oh, that's what dying is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, when the uninstructed commoner becomes... he becomes terrified when there is no ground for fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it should be liberating, but for him it's frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same thing they're thinking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: That somebody who is not an uninstructed commoner
[SPEAKER_01]: He starts thinking about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, if it is, it will certainly not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were for me, I couldn't have not doubted it in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: To begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't have put it in question at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's liberty.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes you let go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop appropriating things.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the untrained mind, if he were to think
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not be, and there might not be for me, it will not be, and there will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He experienced terror and fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, well, his lack of instruction means that he still remains fully centered in his sense of self, that he himself now undermined thoroughly through putting it in question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it might not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just, well, people freak out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, nowadays people freak out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Back in the Witherstone, people freaked out.
[SPEAKER_01]: They fall on the ground with their breasts, or their hair is part of that disorder.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you realize... and that's what nature of death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not seeing other people die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not seeing the ending of other people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting in question your own non-ending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or imagining your body dying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's nothing to do with death, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your own mind that does that imagining.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you... you realize that that has arisen on the ground of a... maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, when it doesn't arise in the future, it might not arise in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it doesn't arise in the future, it will not arise as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I will not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's, that's like terrifying for those who still hold that sense of I am, that sense of soul, that sense of the center of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: They, they, they lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we said, by the instructed noble disciple, he does not become terrified.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he, when he, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not terrifying for him to think, it might not be, and there might not be for me, it will not be, and there will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a confirmation of what he already instructed himself in, freedom from suffering.